Guide to the Mobilization for Survival Records TAM.127
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mobilization for Survival Records
circa 1940s-1992
1977-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mobilization for Survival (Organization)
Drucker, Peter
Cagan, Leslie
Argiroff, Philip
TAM.127
65.5 Linear Feet in 64 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 oversize flat box.
Mobilization for Survival (MFS) is a national organization of local disarmament, anti-intervention, safe energy, religious and community organizations working for four goals: abolish nuclear weapons and power, stop military intervention, meet human needs, and reverse the arms race. This unprocessed collection documents the formation of the organization starting in 1977 and captures the activities of past campaigns and the work of local affiliates. The materials from this collection are from both the national office and the New York City Chapter.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Mobilization for Survival (U.S.) and the New York City chapter of Mobilization for Survival in 1984 through the early 1990s. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1985.022, 1989.016 and NPA.2002.040.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Materials appear in the order in which they were received.
Historical/Biographical Note
Mobilization for Survival (MFS) is a national organization of local disarmament, anti-intervention, safe energy, religious and community organizations working for four goals: abolish nuclear weapons and power, stop military intervention, meet human needs, and reverse the arms race. Activities of the organization include arranging educational programs, large teach-ins, development of resource materials, production of a newsletter, planning massive non-violent demonstrations and organizing local MFS chapters. As a multi-issue coalition MFS highlights the connections among nuclear weapons, military spending, and social and economic justice.
Scope and Contents
This unprocessed collection contains newspaper clippings, minutes, publications, flyers, correspondence, newsletters, staff reports and memos, and financial journals. These materials document the formation of the organization starting in 1977 and captures the activities of past campaigns and the work of local affiliates. The materials from this collection are from both the national office and the New York City Chapter.
Separated Materials
Posters were transferred to the the Tamiment Library Poster and Broadside Collection (GRAPHICS 002).
Peace movements -- United States.; Antinuclear movement -- United States.; Civil rights movements -- United States.; Nuclear disarmament.; Protest movements.; Pressure groups |z United States.; Leaflets (printed works); Peace movements -- New York (N.Y.); Antinuclear movement -- New York (State) -- New York.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Notes.; Reports.; Mobilization for Survival (Organization); Drucker, Peter; Cagan, Leslie; Argiroff, Philip
- Inventory
  - Newsletters, Publications, and Correspondence: Armistice, Black Hills & Paha Sapa, CALC - Clergy & Laity, Coalition for Publicly Owned and Democratically Controlled Utility, Seabrook Occupation, A-Bomb Survivors / Victims, American Friends Service Committee, Citizens' Energy, Citizens' Hearing, Keyston Alliance, Catholic Peace Fellowship, Electoral Campaigns--For Political Rights, Keystone Alliance, Community Mailing Services, (Another) Mother's For Peace, Campaign for UN Reform, Conference Proposals '84, National Conference, Tour, Rally Committee, 1979-1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Mailing Lists, Publications and Leaflets, Art Work, Anti-Nuclear War Demonstration Files, Continuations Committee, Conference Evaluations, Leaflets, Endorsement Letters, Financing Files, Demonstration Files, 1977-1982 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Newspapers, Mobilizer Articles, Leaflets, Solidarity Day & Petitions, Senate Subcommittee on Terrorism, U.S. Department of Transportation, American Friends Service Committee, Live Without Trident/Trident to Life Campaigns, Nuclear Weapons Facilities Task Force, People's Salt III, Plutonium, Wind Energy, Hiroshima--Japan, Human Rights International, Iran-Afghanistan Crisis: Emergency Response, Women and the Peace Movement, Nuclear Regulatory Commission (NRC), Nuclear Legislation, Nukes -- Economy & Jobs, 1977-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Newsletters, Articles, Accounts Received: Central America activity, Nuclear Demonstrations,National Conference '82, Hiroshima/Nagasaki, "The Day After", 1980-1984 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, Newsletter, Demonstration Materials: Nukes, Policy, Military, 1978-1982 (Box 5)
  - New York Metropolitan SSD Campaign Meeting Minutes (Jan 7), Reports and Newsletters: Nuclear Energy General Information, MFS Staff Review, MFS Correspondence, Press Releases, 1977-1981 (Box 6)
  - Newsletters, Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence: Nuclear Victims, Nuclear Transport, Nuclear Waste and Reprocessing, Disarmament, 1978-1982 (Box 7)
  - National Conference, Newspaper Clippings, Bills, Affiliated Organizations & NGOs, 1978-1982 (Box 8)
  - Minutes (May 27 Task Force), Correspondence, Notes, Campaigns, Memorandum, Newspaper Clippings, Bills, Anti-Nuclear Demonstrations, Solar Energy, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - Disarmament, World Peace Organizations, Assemblies, War Resisters: Organizational Materials, Correspondence, Newsletters, Anti-Nuclear Proliferation, Petty Cash, 1977-1981 (Box 10)
  - Linda Rodolitz Homeport Files: Correspondence, Newsletters, Safety Study ('88), Newspaper Clippings, Lawsuits and Testimony, Government Reports (Kaku Nuclear Accident), 1980s (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, Reports, Newspaper Clippings: Homeport and Shipping, GAO--Nuclear Weapons and Energy, Navy Ships and Plans, Harbor Publications, Emergency Control Board, 1985-1991 (Box 12)
  - Newsletters, Organizational Summaries, Legal Briefs, Newspaper Clippings, City Projects, Event Planning, Congressional Hearings, GAO and Department of the Navy, 1985-1991 (Box 13)
  - Department of the Navy Reports: Homeporting, Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, Leaflets, Legal Material, Press Packets, Press Releases and Editorial Materials, City Council Resolutions, 1986-1991 (Box 14)
  - MFS Bills and Check Stubs & Petty Cash, Jul 1977-Aug 1978 (Box 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings: Shipping Union/Strike, National Maritime Union, 1940s (Box 16)
  - Newsletters, Correspondence, MSF Local and Regional, MSF Conference Material: Nuclear Disarmament, Leaflets, Publicity, 1977-1984 (Box 17)
  - Conference Notes from 1977, Conference Follow-ups, Local Newsletter, Democratic Agenda, Mailing Lists, Notes, and Reports + Job Reports 1983, 1977-1979 (Box 18)
  - Coalition For a Nuclear Free Harbor, West Side Tenants and Urban Renewal, World Trade Center, and Yorkville: Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, and Reports, 1960-1984 (Box 19)
  - Minutes of the M.F.S. Draft Resistance Task Force ('82), Coordinating Committee, Task Force, and Campus Outreach, Newspaper Clippings, Mailing and Media Lists, 1979-1982 (Box 20)
  - Mobilizer Past Agendas, Letters, and Articles, Demonstration Material, Records, Notes, Personnel Files, Endorsement Requests, Job Reports and Proposals, 1979-1982 (Box 21)
  - Jobs With Peace Receipts, Petitions, Mailing Lists, Newspaper Clippings, Newsletters, and Disarmament Times`, 1982-1983 (Box 22)
  - Legal Briefs and Lawsuits: Department of the Navy, 1986-1989 (Box 23)
  - Program Files, Newsletters, Publications, Leaflets, Response Surveys, 1991-1992 (Box 24)
  - Bluerdige, Groundzero, Land / Leaf, Sane-Puget Sound, Peace Projects, 1984 National Conference, Correspondence, Staff Meetings (1980s), Emergency Response Network, Facilitator Meetings, Arms Build Up at Sea, Abia -- America Peace Tour (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, Reports, Newspaper Clippings, Homeport, Board Estimates, Individual Files, Nuclear Safety Study Notes, 1985-1990 (Box 26)
  - International Correspondence and Files & Postage Receipts & Employee Taxes, 1979-1982 (Box 27)
  - Congressional Record & Files Re: Base Closing and Hearing, Committee Reports, and Legal Files, 1988-1991 (Box 28)
  - Campaign Materials, Disarmament, International Trip, Weapons Facility Listings, IPCC Meeting (Dec 1989) -- pt. I, 1988-1990 (Box 29)
  - Past Campaigns: Leaflets, Newspaper Clippings, Flyers, Correspondence, Publicity Material, Conference Files, International Communication, 1987 (Box 30)
  - Community Action Materials and Committee Files: Nuclear and Atomic Responsibility, Citizens Committee and Alliance, AESC, CDAS, Taskforce for Sexism, Middle East, Foreign and Military Policy, 1979-1982 (Box 31)
  - Affiliate Mailings, Coordinating Committee Elections, Staff Mailings, Interim Committee, Key Contacts, Staff Reports, FEC Complaints, 1987-1988 (Box 32)
  - Action Committees: Prescott Peace, Peace Makers, Ecology Center of Southern California, Nuclear Freeze Committee, Alliance for Survival, San Jose Peace Center, Florida Coalition for Peace and Justice, Hawaii Education for Social Resources, Feminist Women's Health, Peace Action, Disarm Now, etc., 1984-1985 (Box 33)
  - Past Campaigns, Speaking Tours, Southeast -- Mid East -- Hibakusha, Japan, Speak Out and Breaking the Silence Campaigns, and 40th Anniversary Event, 1985 (Box 34)
  - MFS Resource List, Local Events, Bibliography, Mailing Lists, Outreach, Public Education, Fliers, Newspaper Articles, Publications and Publicity, Grant Proposal, 1980-1982 (Box 35)
  - Newspapers, Publications, Correspondence, Circulation Material re: MFS US Organizations, Nuclear Regulation and Action Coalitions, Campaign Files, 1979-1982 (Box 36)
  - Newspapers, Newsletters, Correspondence, Strategy Papers, Logistical Information, Children's Guides, Brochures, 1979-1982 (Box 37)
  - Northern Sun Alliance Papers, Fliers, Newsletters, Committees of Concern (Montana, Minnesota, North Carolina, New York, New Jersey, New Mexico, Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island), 1988-1990 (Box 38)
  - Newsletters and Publications on Anti-War Action, Leaflets, Fliers,, Buttons, Stickers, Safety Reports and Guidelines re: Nuclear Facilities, Finances, Bills, Bank Expenses, Ledger Books, 1977-1981 (Box 39)
  - October 22 Planning Committee Meeting Minutes and Agenda, Economic Notes, Environmental Action, and Feminist Newsletters, International News, Reports, and Fliers, and JWP Conference Literature, 1979-1988 (Box 40)
  - Past Campaigns for Peace: US-Soviet, Marches, April Actions: Jobs & Justice, Euromissiles Working Group, Summit Organizing, DIS & DEU Conference, Deadly Connections, D.C. Agenda, C.A. Organizing Guide, A.A. Mailing Lists, 1982-1987 (Box 41)
  - Committee Correspondence, Financial Information, Fieldtrip Reports, Mailings, Task Forces, Event Materials, Newspapers, Publications, Informational Material, Regional Conference Reports, 1979-1988 (Box 42)
  - U.S. Affiliate Materials and Memos, Reports, Publications, Correspondence, Newsletters, National Student Action Center, Journals, Coalitional Information, 1985-1986 (Box 43)
  - Administrative Materials, MFS Affiliates and Mailing Lists, Regional Offices, Interim Committee Organization, Literature and Briefs, 1983-1988 (Box 44)
  - Past Campaigns and Affiliate Files, Conference and Agenda material, Disarmament, Endorsements, Programs, Sustainable Energy, Stop the Restart, Women for Peace, and Background Materials, 1987-1991 (Box 45)
  - National Conference Minutes (1989) Affiliate Mailings, Budget, Field Organization, Committee Meetings, Dues Reports, Direct Mail Files, Mobilizer Contracts, Interim Committee, Key Contact Mailings, International Correspondence, and Convention Materials, Notes, and Phone Banking, 1989-1991 (Box 46)
  - Affiliates to 1986 -- NY-Z, Nuclear Free Zones, Organization Activity: Civil Defense, First Strike Conferences, Calendars, Newsletters, and Event Material, Multistate Committees and Action Groups, Material from Spanish Committees, 1981-1985 (Box 47)
  - State Organizational Materials and Peace Networks, Peace Coalitions, Fliers, Newsletters, Newspapers and Administrative, 1990-1991 (Box 48)
  - Nuclear Reports, Newspaper Clippings, Peace Coalition News, Homeport Bibliography, Correspondence, Resolutions and Legal Correspondence, No Safe Harbor Field Reports, Extensive Newspaper Clippings on Homeport, 1985-1989 (Box 49)
  - Correspondence, Notes, Leaflets, Newspaper Clippings: Monthly Action Calls and Endorsements, International Activity and Coordination, Disarmament, Hiroshima/Nagasaki, Lesbian & Gay Network, and Study Packets, 1985-1986 (Box 50)
  - Newsletters and Publications, Newspapers, Handwritten notes, Action Memorandum, Organizing Parties and Papers, Educational and Coalitional Materials, 1977-1991 (Box 51)
  - Articles, Handouts, Posters, Newsletters, and Handwritten Correspondence, Seminar Material, Special Commissions, Artwork and Design, Student Coalitions, Peace Councils, Task Force, Unity Files, Conferences and Workshops, 1982-1983 (Box 52)
  - Leaflets and Anti-Nuclear Activity/Demonstration Material, Reports on Central American Politics, Mailing Materials, Disarmament and Military Literature, Handwritten Notes, Articles, Financial Figures, Lesbian and Gay Network, Correspondence and Memorandum, Coalitional Calendar and Agenda, Referendum, Fliers for Action, Postal Materials and Letters, Merchandise distribution, Pamphlets, 1979-1984 (Box 53)
  - Correspondence, Newsletters, Fliers, and Pamphlets: Mailing Lists, National Network Action Files, Peace Coalition in Central America and the Caribbean Basin, Christie Institute, Freeze Voters, American Friends Service Committee, 1983-1987 (Box 54)
  - Deadly Connection Slides, International Conferences, Leaflets: Japan, Okinawa, Greece, Lebanon, WRL News, Visual Information Project Slideshow, Euromissile Campaigns, Ban the Bomb Makers, Campaign Against 1st Strike, Euromissile program, 1982-1985 (Box 55)
  - MFS Middle East Program, Task Force Material, Slide Show Scripts, Weapon Network Response: Forms and Coordination Material, Correspondences, Handwritten Notes, Conference Registration Forms, Containment Conference, International Peace Conference, Facsimile, and Print-Outs, 1985-1987 (Box 56)
  - MSF International Organizations and Task Force: Central America, Middle East, Program Reports and Evaluations, Discussion Materials, Memorandum, Correspondence, and Newsletters from Old Affiliates, Affiliate Mailings, Office Procedure Files, Handwritten Notes, Convention Files, Recruitment Material, Action Response Forms, Surveys, and Staff Correspondence, 1977-1987 (Box 57)
  - International and NYC Mobilization for Survival Correspondence and Newsletters, Summer Programs, Mailing and Receiving, Fliers, Newspapers, Handwritten Notes, Poster, 1978-1981 (Box 58)
  - Newsletters, Newspapers, Organizing Material, US Sub-Organizations, Campaigns, Unions, Catholic Workers, Letters and Handwritten Notes, Press Release Material and Samples, 1984-1985 (Box 59)
  - Correspondence, Newsletters, Pamphlets, Financial Statements, Reports, Mailing Lists, Letters, Newspapers, Ending the Targeting Campaign Material, Coalition for Nuclear Disarmament, SEA Alliance, New Mexico, New Jersey, Brooklyn, New York City, Pennsylvania, Dallas, Texas, Tennessee, Dutchess County, Peace Centers, Resource Coalition Files, 1983-1985 (Box 60)
  - Packets, Newsletters, Correspondence, Fliers, Press Clippings, Literature, Handwritten Notes, Event Organization, MFS National Convention Material, Disarmament Action Local Literature and Responses, Newspapers and Mailings, 1983-1985 (Box 61)
  - Mailings, Fliers, Handwritten Notes, Publicity, Updates, Correspondence, Newspaper Articles, Campaign Forms, National Conference Materials, Convention and Demonstration Updates, 1980-1984 (Box 62)
  - Notices and Correspondences, Public Statements, Regional Forms, Bank Statements, NYMFS Media and Media Materials, Newspaper Clippings, Newsletters, Information Centers, North Star Fund, National Committee Correspondence and Organizing Materials, Peace Fellowships and Community Organization, National Lawyers Guild, MFS Office Files, 1979-1981 (Box 63)
  - Fliers, Correspondence, Newsletter, Event Materials, Program Coordination, Pamphlets, Reports and Updates from MFS, 1981-1985 (Box 64, Folder 1-8, Box 68, Folder 1-7, Box 69)
  - Photographs, Negatives, Contact Sheets, and Slides, circa 1979-1992 (Box 65)
  - Peace--Not War: Local Responses, Coupon Returns, National Groups, Media, Speakers Response; Peace with Justice Week; Road Show; April 16th-Tax Day; Tax Day Resistance; Pledge of Resistance: analysis of political situation, clearinghouse, actions, correspondence, executive committee, local campaigns, finances, legal information, local feedback and suggestions, media coverage, MFS involvement, multi-issue coalition, newsletter, nonviolent guidelines, personnel committee, program plans, regional coordinators group, religious nature, national retreat, signal group, Stop the Lies packet, strategy, surveys; Solid Shield Military Maneuvers; Pledge: National Literature, "Incrementals Escalations" piece, structure, prominent signers, local's resources; Pledge of Resistance: National Network, address lists of contacts; New York Misc.; Rural Southern Voice for Peace; SANE; North Carolina Peace Network; Jackson County Citizens for a Nuclear Arm Freeze; Ohio Misc.; Wilington College Peace Resource Center; Tulsa Peace Fellowship; Writers for Peace; Green Revolution; Physicians for Social Responsibility; Philadelphia War Tax Resistance; Penn. Freeze; PANE; Environmental Coalition on Nuclear Power; Del-Aware Unlimited; Pennsylvania Misc,; Rhode Island Misc.; South Carolina Misc.; The National Guard; Highlander Center; Texas Misc.; Austin Peace and Justice Coalition; American Friends Service Committee; Hard Times News; Dallas Advocate; MX Information Center; The Desert Sun; Volunteers for Peace; Citizens Party; Vermont, Misc., 1982-1987 (Box 66)
  - Oversize Drawings, undated (Box 67)